<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Britania expirans or, A brief memorial of commerce humbly offer'd to the Parliament,</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01791</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4813B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217700</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47012333</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47012333</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174297</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01791)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174297)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2682:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Britania expirans or, A brief memorial of commerce humbly offer'd to the Parliament,</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London,</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed 1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Merchants, Foreign --  Great Britain --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commercial policy --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174297:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Britania Expirans</hi> OR, A BRIEF MEMORIAL OF COMMERCE Humbly Offer'd to the Parliament,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed. 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:174297:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:174297:2"/>
            <head>Britannia Expirans.</head>
            <p>TO the End there ſhould be a Commerce amongſt Men, it hath pleas'd God to invite, as it were, one Country to Traffick with another, by the Variety of Things which the one hath, and the other hath not, which the Winds and Sea proclaim;<note place="margin">Quòd &amp; vento gentis locis diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipatas miſcuit &amp; ſua omnia in regiones ita deſcripſit, ut ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarium mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talibus eſſet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ipſos co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercium.</note> and this <hi>Seneca</hi> thought to be a principle Benefit of Nature, that there ſhould be a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Commerce amongſt Men.</p>
            <p>IN what a miſerable condition were the <hi>Netherlanders,</hi> if they receiv'd not a Supply from other Nations; they have nothing of their own, and yet they abound in all things by the Supply and Revenue they receive from other Nations.</p>
            <p>IF any Kingdom under the Sun can ſubſiſt of it ſelf, none has more reaſon to bleſs God than this Iſland of ours, which is richly adorned with variety of all things neceſſary for Mans Life and Welfare, as Corn, Cattle, Fiſh, Fowl, Sider, Wool, Cloth, Leather, Tin, Lead, Iron, Hops, Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Flax, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereby we have not only ſufficient for our Maintenance, but do abundantly ſupply the Wants of other Nations, in a wonderful Variety of our Woollen Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures, Tin, Lead, Leather, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and no one Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity that can be named which we are under an abſolute Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of.</p>
            <p>YET notwithſtanding ſo many excellent and valuable Enjoyments, there is ſo great a power in the Management and Contrivance of Commerce, that no Nation hath ever
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174297:3"/>been under greater Declenſions in Trade, at ſeveral periods of time than ours; which by a Brief Survey of former Times, as well as by a due Conſideration of our preſent, ſeems to have been evidently occaſion'd <hi>By a too great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of Foreign Commodities purchaſt with our Treaſure; And by a too great Indulgence of Foreign Merchants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward</hi> III. laid the Foundation of our Riches, by the Eſtabliſhment of our Woollen Manufactures in <hi>England;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Triceſimo ſepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo</hi> Ed. 3. cap. 9</note> to the carrying on of which Noble Deſign of his, he ſtrictly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd the Wear of our Woollen Manufactures, by ſeveral Ranks and Degrees of People by Sumptuary Laws: He took exact care that Merchants Aliens,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Triceſim. octavo</hi> Edw. 3. cap. 2.</note> who ſold any Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in <hi>England,</hi> ſhould inveſt the Money upon the Growth of this Kingdom; And by his wiſe Conduct in theſe Affairs, he made a conſiderable Advance in the Riches and Glory of <hi>England</hi> in a few Years.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard</hi> II. by the Neglect of his Grand-Fathers Rules loſt ground as faſt, which made a great un-eaſineſs amongſt the <hi>Kentiſh</hi> Men (in which Parts the Cloth-Trade was firſt eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht) even to a Rebellion.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno quinto.</hi> Rich. II. cap. 1.</note> He made <hi>England</hi> a Free Port, and gave a general Invitation by Act of Parliament, to all Merchants Strangers to come with their Goods and Families,<note place="margin">cap. 2.</note> and Trade Freely in all Parts of his Dominions, as well with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Franchiſes as without, by Groſs or Retail, to be under his ſafe Protection, and depart into their own Countries as freely again:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno undecimo</hi> Rich. II. cap. 7.</note> And if any Corporation gave them any diſturbance, they ſhould Forfeit their Charter to the King; which mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in effect, to a general Act of Naturalization; and upon Payment of their Cuſtoms before-hand, he made them a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Abatement: He likewiſe gave them a liberty to Tranſport half their Money.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Decimo quarto,</hi> Rich. II. cap. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>BUT Alas! Theſe miſtaken Politicks in few Years drain'd the Treaſure of this Kingdom to that low Ebb, that this Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Prince was denied a Loan of one Thouſand Pounds
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:174297:3"/>by the City of <hi>London</hi> and forc'd ſhamefully to reſign the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. He married the Lady <hi>Anne</hi> Daughter to the Emperor Charles the Fourth, who very much incouraged her Country-Men the <hi>Bohemians</hi> (to the diſcontent of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) and as the Hiſtorian tells us, ſhe brought in High-Head Attire, picked with Horns, and long-trained-Gowns for Women, a Melancholy Omen in thoſe days; and if we have any Plot carrying on amongſt us at this time, I perſwade my Self it is in this perticular; this being the chiefeſt Seat of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at preſent. <hi>Sampſon</hi> ſet the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> Corn-Fields on Fire with Foxes Tails, and if King <hi>Richard</hi> by this means was drove out of his Kingdom I can't tell but it may be a likely way to bring in—or no—Pride and Luxury ſeems to bid faire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> IV. Who ſucceeded him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno quarto</hi> Hen. IV. cap. 15.</note> ſoon perceived the miſchief which his Kingdom ſustained by this indulgence to Foreign Merchants and in the Fourth Year of his Reign he oblig'd all Merchants Strangers to beſtow their whole Money upon the Commodities of this Realm; upon forfeiture of any Gold, Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver or Plate which they ſhould carry out, Excepting their reaſonable coſt. And in the next Year it was Enacted,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno quinto</hi> Hen. 4. cap. 7</note> that Merchant-Strangers ſhall be intreated and demeaned within this Realm in the manner form and condition as the Merchant-Denizens be or ſhall be intreated or demeaned in the Parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Sea, upon pain of forfeiture to the King the Goods and Chattels of ſuch Merchant-Strangers.<note place="margin">cap. 9.</note> he likewiſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged Merchant-Aliens to put in Sureties that they would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their Money upon Commodities of this Realm; and likewiſe appointed Officers to inſpect their buyings and ſell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and in the Year 1406. he granted a Charter to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-Adventurers of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> V. In the Fourth Year of his Reign confirms the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Laws.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno quarto</hi> Hen. V. cap. 5.</note> And in the Eighth Year of his Reign he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged every Merchant-Stranger to bring one ounce of Bullion of Gold to the Mint to be Coin'd for every Sack of Wool which he bought, and one ounce of Gold or the vallue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno octavo,</hi> Hen. V. cap. 2.</note> in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174297:4"/>Bullion of Silver for every three pieces of Tin upon forfeiture of the Wool and Tin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> VI. In the Second Year of his Reign ſtrictly enjoin'd Merchant-Alliens to put in Sureties in the Chancery,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno ſecundo</hi> Hen. VI. c. 13.</note> every Company for them of their Company, that none of them ſhould carry any Gold or Silver out of the Kingdom, and if any Proof could be made beyond the Sea upon any Merchant that went over, his Sureties was obliged to make it good in <hi>England.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno octavo</hi> Hen. VI. c. 24.</note> And whereas theſe Merchants-Alliens had obtained at this time a Credit with many of their Merchandizes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by great loſſes fell upon the Manufacturers, it was Enacted, That no Credit ſhould be given by any Manufactuerer to ſuch Merchant-Alien upon forfeiture of his Goods.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Decimo octavo</hi> Hen. VI. cap. 4.</note> In the Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Year of this Reign a farther Expedient was us'd to prevent the Exportation of their Bullion, The Major, Bailif or Chief Officer of every City where any Merchant-Alien ſhould repair was ordered to Aſſign to every ſuch Merchant-Alien an Hoſt or Surveyor, who was to ſurvey all his Buyings and Sellings and Regiſter them into a Book and certifie them into the Exchequer and to have Two Pence in the Pound for all his Merchandiſes bought and ſold; but in this Act the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of <hi>Almaine</hi> were Exempted which was a Company of Foraign Merchants Eſtabliſhed in <hi>England</hi> by <hi>Henry</hi> III. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Hans</hi> Towns in <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> for ſome Extraordinary ſervice they did in thoſe days.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward</hi> IV. Took a more Effectual way to the cure of this evil after the Example of <hi>Edward</hi> III. by appointing what kind of Apparel Men and Women of every Vocation and Degree ſhould wear,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno tertio</hi> Edw. IV. cap. 5</note> which took away the Temptation of Exporting our Coin and Bullion.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno tertio,</hi> cap. 3.</note> He likewiſe Prohibited by Law the Importation of ſeveral wrought Manufactures, particularly wrought Silk. If any <hi>Engliſhman</hi> or <hi>Welch-man</hi> ſhall bring in,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno tertio</hi> cap. 1.</note> or carry forth any Merchandize in Alien-Ships, if he may have Freight in a Denizen-Ship, he ſhall Forfeit his Merchandize, which was an excellent ſtep to the ſafeguard
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:174297:4"/>of the Kingdom at that time. And in this Law a Penalty was laid upon any Perſon that ſhould wind up any Deceit in Wool.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno quarto</hi> Ed. 4. cap. 1.</note> He likewiſe took exact Care that no Deceit ſhould be uſed in making of Cloth, that the Work People ſhould not be impoſed upon, with extraordinary Weight, Paid with Commodities inſtead of Money.</p>
            <p>HE made a Limitation in the Buying of Wool,<note place="margin">Anno quarto <hi>cap. 3.</hi>
               </note> in favour of the Manufactures. He confirm'd the Charter of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant Adventurers of <hi>England,</hi> and call'd in Queſtion the Charter of the Forreign Merchants of <hi>Almaine,</hi> or the <hi>Still<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard;</hi> which diſguſted the Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> ſo far, that he put out a Proclamation, for the Baniſhment of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cloths out of his Dominion: Upon which a Law was made, that no Merchandizes of the Growth, or Workmanſhip,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno quarto</hi> Ed. 4. cap. 5.</note> of any of the Countries ſubject to the Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> ſhall be brought into this Realm, until he revoke the Proclamation, in which, he was forc'd to comply: And what Advance was made in this Kings Reign, from this juſt Foundation of Trade, and Prudent Management, I leave to the more Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to conſider: He laid a ſtrict Reſtraint upon Gamings;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno decimo ſept.</hi> E. 4. cap. 3.</note> and in the Twenty Second Year of his Reign, he made a new Sumptuary Law about Apparel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard</hi> III. who ſucceded him, made many good Laws, in favour of his own natural born Subjects, in direct oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the incroachments of Aliens, in robbing them of their Imployments, by the Importation of Forreign wrought Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno primo</hi> Rich. 3. cap. 4.</note> and Settlement in <hi>England</hi> in our eaſy Handicraft Imployments; leaving the moſt laborious, as going to Plow, or Cart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to our own Subjects, as is Expreſt in the ſaid Law. The <hi>Italian</hi> Merchants were particularly Complain'd of at this time, as <hi>Venetians, Florentines, Apulians, Cicilians, Lucaners,</hi> &amp;c. by which Law, no Alien could Exerciſe any Handicraft Trade, without being Servants to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, or depart the Realm.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:174297:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> VII. was more exact in this particular than any of his Predeceſſors:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno primo</hi> Hen. 7. cap. 2.</note> By the Second Law he made, he enjoin'd Aliens made <hi>Denizens,</hi> by Letters Pattents, or by Acts of Parliaments, to pay Aliens Duties; in the next place it was Enacted, that no Goods ſhould be Enter'd, but in the Name of the true Owners of the Goods, upon Forfeiture of the Goods, Impriſonment,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tertio.</hi> Hen. 7. cap. 7.</note> and to be Fined at the Kings Pleaſure; a Law (reſpecting the true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt) which deſerv'd to be wrote in Letters of Gold.<note place="margin">cap. 11.</note> He ſuffered no Cloth to be Tranſported, until it was Barbed, Rowed and Shorne, and Confirm'd the Charter of the Merchant Adventurers of <hi>England.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno quarto</hi> Hen. 7. cap. 10.</note> For the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of our Navigation, it was Enacted, that no Perſon ſhould Fraight in a Strangers Ship, to be brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Realm or carried out,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno undecimo</hi> Hen. 7. cap. 14.</note> if he may have ſufficient Fraight in the ſame Port in a <hi>Denizens</hi> Ship: And after Ten Years Experience he renewed the Law, to oblige Aliens made De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizens, to pay the ſame Duties as if they were Aliens. Trade being thus Setled in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> IV. upon juſt and fair Grounds, and carried on with all ſtrictneſs, in the juſt Right and Favour of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, until the end of this Reign: It produc'd a ſtrange alteration of Affairs; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Richard</hi> II. was denied a Loan of a Thouſand Pounds, there was now left in the Treaſury, One Million Eight Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd Thouſand Pounds,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno ſecundo</hi> Hen. 6. cap. 13.</note> which made of our Money above Three Millions; a Pound Troy of Silver being limited by Law, in the Second Year of <hi>Henry</hi> VI. not to be Sold above Thirty Shillings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. took quite contrary meaſures; and which is very remarkable, Merchants Aliens became as much the Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of this Reign.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Decimo nono</hi> Hen. 7. cap. 22.</note> At the death of <hi>Henry</hi> VII. a former Law which prohibited Men of <hi>Chalice,</hi> to be Factors for Merchants Aliens living in <hi>England,</hi> was repeal'd; as likewiſe all Laws, Ordinances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> made in derogation of the Merchants of the <hi>Stilliard,</hi> in the Firſt Year of this Reign. The Law made in the Third Year of <hi>Henry</hi> VII. which obliged all Perſons, to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174297:5"/>enter their Goods in the true Proprietors Name, was likewiſe repeal'd. In the Fifth Year of this Reign,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno primo</hi> Hen. 8. cap. 2.</note> a Liberty was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to Tranſport any Cloth, without being fully Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factur'd, under the value of <hi>Five Marke,</hi> which was a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Rate according to the value of their Coin; upon this pretence, that when they were brought beyond the Seas,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno quinto</hi> Hen. 8. cap. 3.</note> and put into Colours, they muſt be new dreſt, barbed, ſhorne and rowed; ſo natural is it for Merchants of all Countries to Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour their own Subjects. In the Fourteenth Year of this Reign, Strangers Artificers were allowed to Exerciſe their Trades in <hi>England,</hi> contrary to the Law made in the Reign of <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> III. which occaſioned ſo great Diſcontent in <hi>England,</hi> that a Decree made in the <hi>Star Chamber</hi> was put forth,<note place="margin">21 Hen, VIII.</note> to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit all Strangers not made <hi>Denizens,</hi> to keep Houſe or Shops: In the Thirty Second Year of this Reign, Aliens Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties was taken off, for a certain time, by the Kings Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which gave that Advantage to Merchants Aliens,<note place="margin">22 cap. 18.</note> that our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchandize was almoſt rooted out, and our <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Navigation very much ſunk. Forreign Merchants of the <hi>Stilliard,</hi> Shipt off at this time, above <hi>Forty Thouſand</hi> Cloths a Year, and our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants not <hi>Four Thouſand;</hi> and moſt that was Exported and Imported, was in Forreign Botoms, which is <hi>Verbatim</hi> expreſt in the Journals of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> VI.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward</hi> VI. (of Bleſſed Memory) us'd all Endeavour to retrieve what his Father loſt, by Eſtabliſhing Trade upon a juſt and honeſt Baſis, in the right of his own Subjects; and in the Year 1552. the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants being brought to this low Ebb in Trade, put in their complaint to the King and Council againſt theſe <hi>Merchants Tutonicorum</hi> (as they ſtil'd themſelves) and they gave in their Anſwer to the ſaid Complaint upon the Eighteenth Day of <hi>January,</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>25th</hi> their Anſwer was deliver'd to ſome Learned Council to peruſe it; upon the Eighteenth day of <hi>February</hi> the Merchant-Adventurers put in their Replication to the ſaid Anſwer; and upon the Twenty Third a Decree was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174297:6"/>made by the Board, that upon Knowledge and Information of their Charters, they had found, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That they were no ſufficient Corporation; <hi>Secondly,</hi> That their Names, Numbers, and Notions were unknown: <hi>Thirdly,</hi> When <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the Fourth did reſtore them to their Privileges, it was upon the condition that they ſhould cover no Foreigners Goods, which they had done: For theſe Conſiderations, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence was given, That they had forfeited their Liberties, and were to be no more than Strangers. Upon the 28th Day came Ambaſſadors from <hi>Hamburgh, Lubeck,</hi> and the Regent of <hi>Flanders,</hi> to ſpeak upon the behalf of theſe Merchants <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonicorum.</hi> And upon the Second of <hi>March</hi> the Anſwer for the Ambaſſadors was committed to the Lord Chancellor, the two Secretaries Sir <hi>Robert Bowes</hi> and Sir <hi>John Baker,</hi> Judge <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague Griffith,</hi> Solicitors <hi>Goſnald, Goodrick,</hi> and <hi>Brooks;</hi> it remained under Conſideration until the Firſt day of <hi>May,</hi> and then the Merchants <hi>Tutonicorum</hi> received their full Anſwer, confirming the former Judgment of the Council. This gave great Encouragement to <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men to come into the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Merchant-Adventurers. In <hi>October</hi> 3. following there met Three hundred Merchant-Adventurers of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and lent <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth Forty thouſand Pounds to be paid in <hi>Flanders;</hi> and they Ship'd off at that time Forty thouſand Cloths. Our Woollen Manufactures at this time were wonderfully debaſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno quinto &amp; ſexto</hi> Edw. 6. cap. 6.</note> as appears by the Preamble of the Statute made in the ſame Year. Gold was paid at advance Prices at the ſame time; and I think there was never more effectual Means uſed in any Reign, to diſcourage the Profuſeneſs which this Kingdom was led into,<note place="margin">cap. 19.</note> in the long Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth. To prevent the Abuſes and Diſorders in Ale-Houſes and Tippling-Houſes, a Power was given by Law to the Juſtices of Peace, to Remove, Diſcharge, and put away common ſelling of Ale and Beer, as they ſhall think convenient; and none allowed without giving Bond and Surety againſt uſing unlawful Games,<note place="margin">Anno quinto &amp; ſexto <hi>Epw. 6. cap. 25.</hi>
               </note> and for maintaining good Order and Rule.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:174297:6"/>
            <p>AND whereas at this time great numbers of Taverns were ſet up in back-Lanes, Corners, and ſuſpicious Places within the City of <hi>London,</hi> which produced many Inconveniencies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno ſeptimo</hi> Edw. 6. cap. 5.</note> much Evil Rule, and common reſort of miſrul'd Perſons. The Price of <hi>French</hi> Wine was limited to Eight Pence a Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon at the moſt.</p>
            <p>AND the number of Taverns reduced to Forty in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and no Perſons to keep any Wine in their Houſes under ſuch Qualifications. Theſe had been the moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual means to diſcourage Profaneneſs and Imorality, ſo often recommended by His Majeſty. <hi>Sine cerere &amp; Bacco friget Venus.</hi>—And I think I may ſay we have had Forty new erected Taverns in the City of <hi>London,</hi> ſince our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, made out of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants Houſes: A very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious Accommodation to Merchant Aliens.</p>
            <p>Queen <hi>Mary</hi> in the Firſt Year of her Reign made a good ſtep to regulate Perſons in their Habits, according to their Profeſſions and Employments. Whoſoever ſhall wear Silk in or upon his Hat, Bonet, Girdle, Scabbard, Hoſe, Shooes, Spurleather, ſhall be three Months impriſoned, and forfeit 10 <hi>l.</hi> except Mayors, Aldermen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If any Perſon know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Servant to offend, do not put him out of his Service within Fourteen Days, or do retain him again,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno primo</hi> Ph. &amp; Mar. c. 2.</note> he ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit 100 <hi>l.</hi> This Counſel would never have conſented to the vaſt Charge and Hazard of our Fleet in the <hi>Straights,</hi> to bring home this Commodity. There was an attempt made in this Reign by the Foreign Merchants of the Stilliard to regain their Liberties by the Favour of King <hi>Philip,</hi> but it proved ineffectual. In the Year 1557 we loſt <hi>Calais,</hi> which of a long time had been the chief Mart of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Goods.</p>
            <p>Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> confirmed the Charter of the Merchant-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers of <hi>England</hi> and added <hi>Hambrough, Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Frizland</hi> to their Charter and upon Stipulation with the Town of <hi>Hambrough,</hi> as large Priviledges are granted to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Factory as they had in former Time at <hi>Calais</hi> a very
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174297:7"/>commodious Place to the Service of <hi>Germany.</hi> In the firſt Year of Her Reign ſhe revived the Law made by <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno primo</hi> Eliz. cap. 11.</note> that no Perſon, Denizen nor Stranger, do take upon him to Enter or Do, or Cauſe to be Entred, any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Goods coming In or going Out, in the Name or Names of any other Perſon or Perſons, than the very true Owner or Owners of the Goods, upon Forfeiture of the Goods; and at this time Aliens Duties were called the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Revenue of the Crown.</p>
            <p>In the next Place She made an effectual Law to preſerve the Imployment of our Navigation,<note place="margin">cap. 13.</note> by obliging all Perſons, that Ship'd any Goods upon Foreign Bottoms, to pay Aliens Duties: In this Law She limited the Merchant-Adventurers to two Shippings a Year and no more. In the Fifth Year of Her Reign a Law was made to prevent any Credit which ſhould be given with Foreign Goods,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno quinto</hi> Eliz. cap. 6.</note> appertaining to the Cloathing or Adorning of the Body, by rendring the Perſon that Sold them uncapable to recover his Money. In the Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Year of Her Reign, She obliged every Perſon above the Age of Seven Years to wear upon the Sabbath-Day upon their Head a Cap of Wooll, Knit, Slick'd and Dreſſed in <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Decimo tertio</hi> Eliz. cap. 19.</note> except Maids, Ladies, Gentlewomen, Noble Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages, and every Lord, Knight, and Gentleman of Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Mark Land, and their Heirs and ſuch as have bore Office of Worſhip in any City, Borough, Town, Hamblet or Shire, and the Wardens of the Worſhipful City of <hi>London.</hi> upon pain to Forfeit for every Days not wearing, Three Shillings and Four Pence: So careful was She to preſerve the Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Her own Subjects.</p>
            <p>When each Woman in <hi>England,</hi> in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, was a ſtanding Revenue to the King of <hi>France,</hi> by his <hi>Alamodes</hi> and <hi>Luſtrings;</hi> this was the laſt Sumptuary Law made in <hi>England,</hi> and what Figure <hi>England</hi> made in the World, and how firm this Queen ſtood in the true Intereſt of the Populacy, I need not multiply Words to relate.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:174297:7"/>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> I. in the Firſt Year of his Reign, Repeals all ſumptuary Rules,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno primo</hi> Jac. I. cap. 25.</note> and let looſe the Reins to Exceſs in Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel and Wine, in Favour of <hi>Scotland;</hi> He likewiſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed the Law againſt <hi>Hawkers</hi> and <hi>Pedlers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">cap. 33.</note> made in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, and gave Liberty to Tranſport our Wooll under the Cuſtom of Thirty three Shillings Four Pence of every Merchant born Denizen for a Sack, which contain'd Eighteen Score; and Three Pound Six Shillings Eight Pence for every Merchant Stranger not born Denizen. And I think I need not ſpend time to ſhew how this Phyſick work'd by degrees amongſt our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects, but am well aſſured by one <hi>Miſſelden</hi> a Merchant, that wrote in the Year 1622 a little Tract upon the Decay of the Trade in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> That <hi>Indian</hi> Commodities was got into <hi>England</hi> as much in thoſe Days as in ours, which he then urged as the chief Cauſe of the Scarcity of Money in <hi>England</hi> at that time. In the Seventh Year of this Reign we had an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſate, which gave a Subſidy to the King (out of all Goods and Merchandizes) of Two Shillings and Eight Pence in the Pound, to be paid by every Perſon born within this Realm of <hi>England;</hi> and Five Shillings and Four Pence by every Alien and Stranger born out of the King's Obei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance: Four Shillings in the Pound out of all Land in the Hands of all Perſons born under the Kings Obeiſance; and Eight Shillings in the Pound out of all Lands in the Hands of Aliens, Denizens or not Denizens, born out of the King's Obeyſance. How ſar this diſtaſted the Court at that time I can't tell, but no Parliament was called until Fourteen Years after. <hi>Foelix quam faciunt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt did nothing in Trade for the good of his Subjects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> put out a Proclamation upon the Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Day of <hi>May</hi> 1655, to ſupport the Merchant-Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers of <hi>England</hi> in their Trade, and particularly Eſtabliſhed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174297:8"/>a Staple for <hi>Engliſh</hi> Goods at <hi>Dordrecht</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> which place was agreed upon between the Fellowſhip of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-Adventurers of <hi>England,</hi> and the Magiſtrates of that City; he ſtrictly forbad any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Woollen-Manufactures to be carried to any other Parts of <hi>Holland;</hi> and at this time our <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade was quite ſunk. Lands in <hi>England</hi> was never higher than at this time; nor ever a more general Imployment for our Poor; which brought much Riches in few Years into this Kingdom, and gave ſuch ſatisfaction to our Artificers, that thoſe times are ſtill remembred with Veneration to this very day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the II. laid the Foundation of our Misfortunes in Trade, by the Settlement of the Book of Rates ſo much in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of <hi>France,</hi> and our <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company; particularly upon the Article of Linnens, which is a Commodity of great Uſe in <hi>England,</hi> and our Plantations, and natural to be rais'd in <hi>France, Flanders</hi> and <hi>Germany;</hi> which three Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſtand in Competition with this Commodity, and the leaſt favour in Cuſtoms given to any one, muſt needs diſtance the other, <hi>Flemiſh, Gentiſh, Iſingam, Overiſils, Rouſe, Brabant, Embden,</hi> Frieze-Cloth, Bag-Holland, Brown Holland, all <hi>Flanders</hi> Linnens was charg'd at <hi>three pence per Ell</hi> Cuſtom; Fine Broad Dowlas of <hi>France,</hi> the Piece containing one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſix Ells, was charged at <hi>Five Shillings,</hi> a little above one <hi>half-penny per Ell;</hi> and all other ſorts of Linnen in like proportion; a piece of fine Lawns containing thirteen <hi>Ells</hi> of <hi>Germany</hi> Linens, was charged at <hi>ſix Shillings</hi> Cuſtom, a piece of fine Muſlin or Callico from the <hi>Eaſt-Indies, ſix-pence per piece.</hi> This impoveriſht the Linen-Manufactures in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and as much advanc'd the <hi>French,</hi> which made way to the <hi>French</hi> Conqueſts in thoſe Parts. As the Conſumption of <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> Linnens leſſen'd in <hi>England,</hi> the conſumption of our Woollen-Manufactures ſunk in a like proportion in thoſe Parts; which in the Year 1663, made the Woollen-Manufacturers Petition the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the Merchant-Adventurers having large
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:174297:8"/>Stocks of Cloth upon their hands which they could not Sell; the Parliament at that time Addreſſeth the King to make a Trial of a Free-Trade, which was then ſeconded by ſome other <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants who were not Free of that Company, who prevail'd, and with ſtrained, falſe Cloth made ſome advantage to themſelves in <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> at the firſt time; but this Gap being open'd to the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Interlopers were totally rooted out by the <hi>Dutch</hi> and other Nations, and Agents for them ſettled in <hi>England,</hi> which is well in Memory: Wooll ſunk from twenty five ſhillings <hi>per Todd</hi> to fourteen, and the other produce of Land in like proportion; and this un-eaſineſs gain'd another Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch;</hi> In the twenty fifth Year of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. a Law was procured to take off Aliens-Duties, which was the Fatal Stroke to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize and Navigation, which by this Means was preſerved from the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> It is well remembred how all <hi>French</hi> Commodities were encourag'd in <hi>England,</hi> Linnen, Clarets, Brandy, Silks, Gauzes, nay, Druggetts made of our own Wooll, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> could now turn their Clarets and Brandy into Perpetuana's and <hi>Colcheſter</hi> Bays, and ſend them to <hi>Spain</hi> upon as good Terms as any <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and have Home Pieces of Eight in Return, and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Wooll in a ſettled Courſe of Trade, which the King of <hi>France</hi> improved to the very utmoſt, and upon a Modeſt Computation, above a quarter part of the Wooll of this Kingdom was carried into <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>James</hi> the II. did nothing relating to Trade in his Reign; His Martial Genius led him to the execution of that which was prepar'd in the laſt. And upon this foot we ſtood at the Revolution, at which time we could not reaſonably promiſe our ſelves any ſafety without leſſening the power of <hi>France,</hi> who, by the enjoyment of theſe advantages in Trade ever ſince the beginning of the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> was come to a prodigious heighth. The ſtop of our Wooll, the Improvement of our Manufacture; <hi>Engliſh</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:174297:9"/>Merchandize and Navigation, the natural ſupply of our Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to a thinking Politician, might have been a good help to the attainment of this End; but nothing alas! of this could be done without touching the Intereſt of <hi>Holland;</hi> and in the heat of theſe Affairs, the Vogue of <hi>a free Trade, a free Trade!</hi> Lil-ly Bullero, <hi>a free Trade</hi>— ſo much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, that inſtead of making up our Mounds which were pull'd down in K. <hi>Charles</hi> II's Reign, like the inconſiderate <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jans,</hi> we pull'd down our Walls to let them in, and uſher'd in a Clauſe by way of Rider, in a pretended Bill to prevent the Exportation of Wooll to the Deſtruction of our Factories abroad; the Father deſtroy'd his own Son, and all oppoſition to this Intereſt in Trade, has hitherto prov'd ineffectual. A numerous Petition the very next Year to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Tranſportation of Wooll by taking off the Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and to redreſs ſome Grievances in Trade, from a County then declining in Trade, but ſince miſerable, was preſented to the Parliament, and a Bill was order'd in upon the Prayer of the Petition, which being fram'd to the diſadvantage of this Intereſt, was the Firſt Year baffled; a ſecond attempt made; a third, a fourth, it ſtill lay upon the Table, like the Lame Man at the Pool of <hi>Betheſday;</hi> and when any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was made to bring it to a Hearing, ſome more important Affair always ſtept in— A Bill for the <hi>Royal Luſtring Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi>— To Naturalize <hi>Solomon Amey,</hi> a <hi>Frenchman</hi> (who has ſince cheated our Clothiers of a conſiderable Sum, and wrote them from <hi>Holland,</hi> if they will not take Ten Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in the Pound he will pay none) to out of an Entail— to cut a River—
<q>O quanto plauſu! quibus haec complectimur ulnis!</q> and, which was very remarkable, that Member which was moſt zealous for this foreign Intereſt, ſeldom miſt Preferment, <hi>Sr— S— Sr—Y.— Mr. C.</hi>— or any other that the Coat will fit. If the Diſappointments in the Funds prolong'd the War two Years, had good Care been taken in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:174297:9"/>I am ſatisfied the War had ended four Years ſooner. Our Poor coſt Seven Hundred Thouſand Pound in Charity <hi>per Annum,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> earn'd as much out of our Wooll.</p>
            <p>How often was the Conſideration of Trade recommended by His Majeſties Moſt Gracious Speech, which part of it was like the Rabbins <hi>Greek— Non poteſt legi.</hi> Our Saviour, in a Parable, tells us of a Man that had two Sons, and he came to the one and ſaid, go work in <hi>my</hi> Vinyard, and he anſwer'd, (upon what ſcruple I can't tell) <hi>I will not, but afterwards</hi> upon due conſideration, <hi>repented and went;</hi> he ſaid likewiſe to the other, and before the Words were out of his Mouth, he ſeems to Anſwer, <hi>I go Sir— but never went.</hi> I think I may fairly borrow the Words of <hi>Juvinal,</hi> and aſſert them in a great deal of Truth at this time, with a little Variation; <hi>Et ſpes &amp; ratio bonorum in Caeſare tantum: Solus enim artifices hac tempeſtate Egenos reſpexit—</hi> Sat. 7. And true Love of this kind always begat Love in <hi>England,</hi> which to Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was a better ſecurity than a Standing Army. <q rend="inline">War, we are told is now become a Trade, and Management the Principle Art of War; and ſuch Qualifications needful to our Souldiery, as for Men ſet apart to the Goſpel.</q> I can't but diſagree with theſe Qualifications from our late Experience, when the Army began to Preach as well as Fight, we had ſoon no King. It muſt be confeſt, that the Power of <hi>France</hi> was ſo great, that it made up a full Apprentiſhip in War to bring this Potent Prince within his due Bounds, and no Prince but ours, could ever have turn'd the Tide of his Ambition. Notwithſtanding which it doth not follow, that Souldiery ſhall be a ſtanding Trade in <hi>England,</hi> becauſe it was never thought to be our Natural Strength; and if it be allowed, That <hi>France</hi> came to this extraordinary Greatneſs by the advantages which he enjoyed by the Manufacture of our Wooll, the large conſumption of his <hi>Linnens, Alamodes, Claret, Brandy, Paper, &amp;c.</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> the whole Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, and King <hi>James;</hi> and upon the other hand, that <hi>England, Germany</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> have been impoveriſht by a leſſening the conſumption of our Woollen
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:174297:10"/>Manufactures, and the Linnens of <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> it doth follow, that this Greatneſs of <hi>France</hi> was purely acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental (Money being the Sinews of War) and if ſo, Land-Forces in <hi>England</hi> are to be eſteemed no more than acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, and ſafely to be laid aſide when theſe extraordinary ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of the <hi>French</hi> Treaſure are intercepted, which is now in our power to do, <q rend="inline">But <hi>France</hi> is at this time too ſtrong a Match in <hi>Flanders</hi> for any ſingle Nation in <hi>Europe,</hi> not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting <hi>England.</hi>
               </q> Which may be allowed, yet I doubt not, but <hi>Spain,</hi> the Emperor and <hi>Holland</hi> are able to ballance his Greatneſs, the Emperor being diſengaged in his War with the <hi>Turks,</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> having obtained a Revenue out of <hi>Ergland</hi> ſince the War which would hugely augment their Forces if need require. Our Souldiers being disbanded, will fall into Employments, which will increaſe our Treaſure; many may come into our <hi>Militia,</hi> and thereby not only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their Exerciſe, but encourage others; and if any thing extraordinary ſhould happen, a ſmall Reward would gain many of them again; and an Army kept in <hi>England</hi> with our Beef, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but few Years, I am of Opinion, would ſhrink at firſt time at the Hardſhips abroad, as new-rais'd-Men has done; and ſuppoſing the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> had been a <hi>Frenchman,</hi> and our Weſtern Manufacturers fluſht in Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, they had ſoon made Dice of his Bones; this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, by his fondneſs of Alliances and Confederacies abroad, ſeem'd to be taken with the Vanity of the Stag, who fell in love with his Horns, and deſpiſed his Legs. And this brings me to the Proof of my Aſſertion.</p>
            <p>And in the Firſt Place I will conſider our Coin, the artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Matter of Commerce, which is ſaid to be the Sinews of War and of State, and I very much doubt in this Point we are <hi>Expiring;</hi> a Common-Wealth is like unto a Private Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, where if the Expence is greater than the Revenue, he muſt needs come behind-hand, which ſeems to be our Caſe at preſent, the <hi>quantum</hi> of our Coined Silver out of our Clipt-Money and Plate, I think was about Five or Six Millions, a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:174297:10"/>very ſcanty allowance to carry on the Commerce of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and if that Tale was to be made good at this time, I would not be the Security for one Million— Upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration firſt of the Price of Bullion, ever ſince the Coinage has been over, which has been from five ſhillings ſeven pence half-penny <hi>per ounce,</hi> to five Shillings three Pence, riſing and falling, at this time about five ſhillings ſix pence, and as the <hi>Exchange</hi> to <hi>Cales</hi> now rules, there is no likelihood of any alteration. The Arrival of the Galeons nor Flota has turn'd the Tyde. The late Act of Parliament for conſolidating our Gold and Silver-Lace has had a very good effect in the increaſe of that Wear in Occular Demonſtration. The Exportation of our Bullion to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> bears an equal proportion to our conſumption of Muzlins and <hi>Indian</hi> Commodities, which is ſo great, that we are forced to ranſack all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> for Silver, which lately diſturbed our rich Neighbours (who are the Pattern of a Free-Trade) fearing that we were about to ſhake the Bank of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> tho not half a ballance to what was Shipped hence to <hi>Holland,</hi> in the prime time of our Clipping, as the Bills of Entry will demonſtrate. When we have been ſo lately in the Sudds by a general Clipping and Exchanging of Broad Money, to expect ſo ſudden an altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that twenty eight pound of Silver in Coin ſhall be paid away to purchaſe twenty five pounds and an half of the ſame Commodity is too great a preſumption, I doubt, whilſt the Refining-Pot knows no diſtinction. Doctor <hi>Lock,</hi> in his Poſition, <hi>That an equal quantity of Silver is always of equal value to an equal quantity of Silver,</hi> I think was ſcarce Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox on either ſide. We may with leſs difficulty be ſlipt out of our Silver Coin than we had to procure it, and the difficulty of former times will I hope, put us upon Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in this matter in due time. The Baniſhment of all Cotton-Linens out of <hi>Enrope</hi> was once propos'd at a Treaty of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> which would be an excellent Expedient at this time, to increaſe the Treaſure of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then our Alliance by a profitable Commerce in our Woollen Manufactures, and the Flaxen Linens of <hi>Flanders, Germany</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:174297:11"/>and <hi>Holland,</hi> which will be the beſt Guard againſt <hi>France;</hi> eſtabliſh a more ſolid Foundation for Charity, and make our Habits more agreeable to our Profeſſion. Had <hi>Dorcas</hi>'s Garments been made of Muſlin, her Name had hardly been memoriz'd by the Tears of the Poor. <hi>Solomon</hi> compares a Vertuous Woman to the Merchants Ships,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 31. v. 14.</note> and I think, no Women were ever ſo exact to the Letter of the Simile as ours in Flag and Sail, extended in levity <hi>a prora puppique,</hi> and if they do not ſo fully anſwer the end of the Simile, as might be wiſht, in bringing home our Treaſure, as is ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly intimated by the Wooll, Flax, Spindle and Diſtaff, I am ſure they contribute very much by their Muſling-Sails, to the carrying of it out; had <hi>Solomon</hi> lived in our days, all his Wiſdom had fail'd him in diſtinguiſhing the Harlot by her Attire. And ſince theſe <hi>Indian</hi> Commodities has made ſo little difference between <hi>Abigail</hi> and my Lady in Habits, the Maſter too often took one inſtead of the other; which may have occaſion'd a greater inconveniency than we are well aware of, in preventing the due reproofs of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancy, thro' fear of a cloſer application at Home. Lectures againſt Pride were Jewels by their rarity in our late Reigns, and hereby this Monſter Pride has made her own Intrenchment.</p>
            <p>The next Point to be conſidered is our Merchandize, in which we are evidently <hi>expiring.</hi> Eight Parts in Ten of the Native Commodities of this Kingdom which are Tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I am well aſſured are bought in <hi>England</hi> by Forein Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, and our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Factories abroad ſunk in a like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, and a very great ſhare of the profit of our eaſie, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail Trades in <hi>England,</hi> is geting into the hands of Aliens of a lower degree. Nay, we have Wooll-brogging <hi>Jews.</hi> It was ſaid in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, that their Names, Numbers and Nations were unknown, and into what a <hi>Babel</hi> are we got into, an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> may ſoon loſe his own Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage upon the Eaſt part of our <hi>Exchange.</hi> I can't but wiſh the Wind may vary from that Point, that we may carry our Merchandize out, and they tarry at home. The
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:174297:11"/>reaſon which was urged in <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh's Reign, was, that when Foreigners had got Eſtates in <hi>England,</hi> they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried them into their own Countries, which is very natural, as our Merchants brought their Eſtates home; but here is the odds, there is a Seminary of Merchants ſtill growing in <hi>England</hi> out of the younger Sons of our Gentry, who have always Fortunes given them by their Friends, when moſt of theſe Foreigners come very light into <hi>England,</hi> wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon Commiſſions, which is now drove very low, and if they take to drink high, inſtead of carying an Eſtate home, in a fair way, they many times make their Fortunes by the loſs of our Manufacturers; get an Eſtate over and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver pay— as Trade is now ſettled, in Advices twice a Week, how all Commodities govern, a <hi>Dutch</hi> or <hi>German</hi> Merchant can manage a Stock in <hi>England</hi> by an Agent of his lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a Garet at a <hi>Packer's</hi> Houſe; or by ſome <hi>Engliſhman</hi> for one <hi>per Cent.</hi> Commiſſion, whilſt his Stock is ſecure from any Taxes— and the whole benefit and influence thereof accrews to his own Countrymen. No Man fixt in a good way of living in his Native Country, will be willing to leave it, and if we muſt make them fat here, I can't but think our own Subjects (by a preſervation of their Rights) will thrive beſt in our own Paſtures. How much <hi>per Cent.</hi> the profit of our Merchandize may be allowed to be, or what Concern it is for us to ſecure this Employment for the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Sons of our Gentry, I ſhall not determine; only conſider briefly the attendant inconveniencies of this alteration to the Publick.</p>
            <p n="1">I. THE Government of Trade is hereby taken out of our hands, which gives double advantage to the Alien in buying of our Goods, and ſelling of his own; as likewiſe, in ſome meaſure the Government of the <hi>Exchange.</hi> No Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon now living, can remember the like loſs that our Nation lately ſuſtained in this particular; twenty five <hi>per Cent.</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage in Remittance of Money to buy Tallies at Five and Forty <hi>per Cent.</hi> and receive Eight <hi>per Cent.</hi> Intereſt, which Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is now ſpent in <hi>Holland,</hi> a hard Article upon us, that ſo
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:174297:12"/>great a part of the Revenue of our Kingdom is ſpent abroad. <hi>Madder</hi> is ſold above double the uſual Price, Spiceries a third part advance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. Since this <hi>Alteration</hi> vaſt quantities of our Wooll has been Tranſported, our Manufactures much debas'd, carry'd off without being fully manufactur'd, and many Goods ſmuggled to the loſs of the King's Cuſtom.</p>
            <p n="3">III. THE ſtrength of our Nation, in caſe of a War is hereby much leſſen'd. Suppoſing a War with <hi>Holland,</hi> and the <hi>Exeter</hi> Serge-Makers wholly depending upon <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchants; they could not ſubſiſt long, when many inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces may be brought in the like Caſe, when the Merchant-Adventurers of <hi>England</hi> took off vaſt quantities of Goods and laid them up to the out-ſide of their Stocks, and being Men of Intereſt borrowed much more for the ſame purpoſe, and the Service they did this Kingdom <hi>Anno</hi> 88, is worthy to be remembred to their honour; when they ſupply'd the Navy-Royal with a whole Ships lading of Powder and Shot from <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> which came luckily, even <hi>in articulo temporis,</hi> when there was a great want thereof; and far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quantities of Cloth has been Ship'd off by this Company than ever was in a looſe, diſorderly Trade, and larger <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Ships employed, which would be of Service in a War.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Hereby the ſharpeſt People of all Countries are let in upon us. After our Coin was par'd to the quick, it was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable to hear the Logical Diſcourſes of our <hi>Coffee-Houſes</hi> upon the intrinſick value of a Guinea, which by the ſtrength of Reaſon was brought up to Thirty Shillings, directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to a Law made in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth; being ſettled a little time at this value, and conſiderable Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments made to our Woollen-Manufacturers for large quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of Goods bought at little or no Advance; the Summer Crop of Wooll bought up, ſome for <hi>Holland,</hi> and another part by our Wooll-boggers; about <hi>Michaelmas</hi> the danger of the Fall of Guineas begin to appear; thoſe that had Wooll remaining upon hand, would not ſell but at a proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable advance, the <hi>Jobbers</hi> held theirs at a like Rate, the Manufacturer is brought upon the Rack, to take the Wooll at this Price, or his Work-People ſtarve; as ſoon as this is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:174297:12"/>done, and Goods came to Market early in the Spring, the Tyde turn'd, all was at Stake if the Price of Guineas was not brought down; the Manufacturers that had the dear Goods upon hand, petition'd the Parliament to ward the Blow, but ineffectual; the Guineas made a trip to <hi>Holland,</hi> which made a ſtop in Trade; the Clothier ſold that Cloth, which he could not afford under 15 <hi>l.</hi> at 10 <hi>l.</hi> ſome at 9 <hi>l.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt thing I ſhall mention to prove my Aſſertion is our <hi>Navigation,</hi> in which particular we are come to a lower Ebb if poſſible; not one Ship in 40 employ'd in our Merchandize to <hi>Holland, Flanders</hi> and <hi>Breme,</hi> and very few to <hi>Hambro</hi> and the <hi>Eaſt-Country,</hi> to which parts two thirds of the <hi>Native Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of this Kingdom are Exported, and a greater ſhare of our Plantation-Goods; a very great increaſe of Shiping at <hi>Breme,</hi> where every Ship which they have advanc'd, have ſunk the Imployment of a Ship in <hi>England.</hi> Moſt Merchants are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in Shiping, and its natural to imploy their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men; how much the ſtrength of our Nation is leſſned in this particular, I leave to the more judicious; the imployment of as many Seamen as would Man a Fleet for our Security, is hereby loſt, who are always within the compaſs of a Poſt-Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter twice a Week, our own Seamen are hereby become Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in our home Seas, which would be of as good ſervice, and as much to be depended upon as if kept in the King's Pay, which Propoſal I take to be the ſame with that of building Work-Houſes for the Imployment of our Poor, whilſt at the ſame time the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French</hi> get a quarter-part of our <hi>Wooll.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nothing in the eye of reaſon) but an effectual ſtop to our <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Luxury,</hi> in a Forein Conſumption (as well upon a <hi>Politick</hi> as a <hi>Religious</hi> account) can ſecure this Kingdom from ruine. The <hi>Dutch</hi> and Forein Nations are actually in the poſſeſſion (in <hi>Merchandize</hi> and <hi>Navigation</hi>) of the profitable part of our <hi>Commerce</hi> in reſpect to the Publick. The Stock remaining in <hi>Engliſh</hi> hands— is chieſly imploy'd in bringing home Materials to maintain this <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Luxury</hi>— and in ingroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all ſorts of Materials to the greater Oppreſſion of our Poor, which Stock being ſtopt upon one hand, will naturally fall into the other, by the Support and Enlargement of our <hi>Hambro, East Country</hi> and <hi>Ruſſia</hi> Companies, under due Regulations. And our Miſery or Welfare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving it ſelf by the actions of <hi>this great Council,</hi> I hope all true <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> will join in hearty Prayers for a Bleſſing upon Your Undertakings, That no more of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects may ſtarve in our Streets.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:174297:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174297:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
